Finding Aid for Howard Bishop Lewis pamphlets and reprints, 1912-1953 and undated
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Howard Bishop Lewis pamphlets and reprints 1912-1953, undated
Lewis, Howard Bishop, 1887-1954.
1 boxes
DA 2; L674.5; P186
Professor of Biological Chemistry and dean of the College of Pharmacy at the University of Michigan.; reprints of scientific articles in areas or biochemistry.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The material was assembled from a number of sources.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Professor of Biological Chemistry and chairman of the department and Dean of the College of Pharmacy at the University of Michigan.
The Howard Bishop Lewis pamphlets and reprints collection consists of reprints of scientific articles, many having to do with metabolism and amino acids and the role of proteins in nutrition.
Subjects:
Biochemistry.; Sulphur--Metabolism.; Cystine.; Methionine.; Protein.
- Pamphlets and Reprints.
  - 1912
    - The behavior of some hydantoin derivatives in metabolism: I. Hydantoin and ethyl hydantoate. (Box 1)
    - The value of inulin as a foodstuff. (Box 1)
  - 1913
    - The behavior of some hydantoin derivatives in metabolism: II. 2-Thiohydantoins. (Box 1)
    - The reaction of some purine, pyrimidine, and hydantoin derivatives with the uric acid and phenol reagents of folin and denis. (Box 1)
  - 1914
    - The influence of inulin on the output of glucose in phlorhizin diabetes. (Box 1)
    - Studies on the synthesis of hippuric acid in the animal organism: I. The synthesis of hippuric acid in rabbits on a glycocoll-free diet. (Box 1)
    - Studies in the synthesis of hippuric acid in the animal organism: II. The synthesis and rate of elimination of hippuric acid after benzoate ingestion in man. (Box 1)
  - 1915
    - The behavior of some hydantoin derivatives in metabolism: III. Parabanic acid. (Box 1)
  - 1916
    - A comparative study of the distribution of urea in the blood and tissues of certain vertebrates with especial reference to the hen. (Box 1)
    - Changes in the urea content of blood and tissues of guinea pigs maintained on an exclusive oat diet. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: I. The relative eliminations of sulfur and nitrogen in the dog in inanition and subsequent feeding. (Box 1)
    - Studies in the synthesis of hippuric acid in the animal organism: III. The excretion of uric acid in man after ingestion of sodium benzoate. (Box 1)
  - 1917
    - The metabolism of sulfur: II. The influence of small amounts of cystine on the balance of nitrogen in dogs maintained on a low protein diet. (Box 1)
    - The phenol excretion of guinea-pigs maintained on an exclusive oat diet. (Box 1)
    - A study of the normal metabolism of the guinea pig. (Box 1)
  - 1918
    - The occurrence of lichenase in the digestive tract of invertebrates. (Box 1)
    - Studies in uric acid metabolism: I. The influence of high protein diets on the endogenous uric acid elimination. (Box 1)
    - Studies in uric acid metabolism: II. Proteins and amino-acids as factors in the stimulation of endogenous uric acid metabolism. (Box 1)
  - 1919
    - The antiscorbutic value of the banana. (Box 1)
  - 1920
    - Amino-acid synthesis in the animal organism. Can nor-leucine replace lysine for the nutritive requirements of the white rat? (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: III. The relation between the cystine content of protines and their efficiency in the maintenance of nitrogenous equilibrium in dogs. (Box 1)
  - 1921
    - The action of nitrous acid on casein. (Box 1)
    - Diet and sex as factors in the creatinuria of man. (Box 1)
    - Lipase studies: I. The hydrolysis of the esters of some dicarboxylic acids by the lipase of the liver. (Box 1)
    - Studies on the synthesis of hippuric acid in the animal organism: IV. A note on the synthesis of hippuric acid in the rabbit after exclusion of bile from the intestine. (Box 1)
  - 1922
    - The hydrolysis of sucrose in the human stomach. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: IV. The oxidation of cystine in the animal organism. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: V. Cysteine as an intermediary product in the metabolism of cystine. (Box 1)
  - 1923
    - Biochemical studies on allantoin: I. The influence of amino-acids on the excretion of allantoin by the rabbit. (Box 1)
    - Lipase studies: II. A comparison of the hydrolysis of the esters of the dicarboxylic acids by the lipase of the liver. (Box 1)
    - Studies in uric acid metabolism: III. The influence of fats and carbohydrates on the endogenous uric acid elimination. (Box 1)
    - Studies in the synthesis of hippuric acid in the animal organism: V. The influence of amino-acids and related substances on the synthesis and rate of elimination of hippuric acid after the administration of benzoate. (Box 1)
    - Studies in the synthesis of hippuric acid in the animal organism: VI. The influence of the protein of the diet on the synthesis and rate of elimination of hippuric acid after the administration of benzoates. (Box 1)
  - 1924
    - Amino acid synthesis in the animal organism: The availability of some caproic acid derivatives for the synthesis of lysine. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: VI. The oxidation of cystine in the animal organism, second paper. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: VII. The oxidation of some sulfur compounds related to cystine in the animal organism. VIII. The behavior of thiophenol and thiocresol in the animal organism. (Box 1)
    - A quantitative study of some organic constituents of the saliva. (Box 1)
    - Some contributions of chemistry to the art and science of medicine. (Box 1)
    - Sulfur metabolism. (Box 1)
  - 1925
    - Insulin. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: IX. The effect of repeated administration of small amounts of cystine. (Box 1)
  - 1926
    - The influence of hydrazine and its derivatives on metabolism: I. The effect of substitution in the hydrazine molecule upon the hypoglycemic action of hydrazine. (Box 1)
    - The influence of hydrazine and its derivatives on metabolism: II. Changes in the non-protein nitrogenous constituents of the blood and in the metabolism of injected glycine in hydrazine intoxication. III. The mechanism of hydrazine hypoglycemia. (Box 1)
    - Lipase studies: III. The hydrolysis of the esters of the dicarboxylic acids by the lipase of the liver. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: X. The determination of cystine in the urine. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: XI. Can taurine replace cystine in the diet of the young white rat? (Box 1)
    - The role of the inorganic elements in nutrition. (Box 1)
  - 1927
    - The absorption and utilization of inulin as evidenced by glycogen formation in the white rat. (Box 1)
    - The cystine content of hair and other epidermal tissues. (Box 1)
    - The distribution of nitrogen in the blood and urine of the turtle (chrysemys pinta). (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: XII. The value or diglycyl-cystine, dialanyl-cystine, and dialanyl-cystine dianhydride for the nutritive requirements of the white rat. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: XIII. The effect of elementary sulfur on the growth of the young white rat. (Box 1)
  - 1928
    - Comparative studies of the metabolism of amino acids. I. Changes in the non-protein nitrogenous constituents of the blood following administration of amino acids. (Box 1)
    - Occurrence of cystine in sweat of cystinurics. (Box 1)
    - Physical development and the excretion of creatine and creatinine by women. (Box 1)
    - Studies in the synthesis of hippuric acid in the animal organism: VII. A comparison of the rate of elimination of hippuric acid after the ingestion of sodium benzoate, benzyl alcohol, and benzyl esters of succinic acid. (Box 1)
  - 1929
    - Comparative studies of the metabolism of amino acids. II. The rate of absorption of amino acids from the gastrointestinal tract of the white rat. (Box 1)
    - Exogenous arginine as the precursor of creatine in the dog. (Box 1)
    - The formation of glycogen in the liver of the young white rat after the oral administration of glycerol. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: XIV. A metabolic study of a case of cystinuria. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: XV. The relation of the protein and cystine content of the diet to the growth of the hair in the white rat. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: XVI. Dietary factors in relation to the chemical composition of the hair of the young white rat. (Box 1)
  - 1930
    - The action of nitrous acid on casein. II. (Box 1)
    - Comparative studies of the metabolism of amino acids: III. The formation of glycogen after oral administration of amino acids to white rats. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: XVII. The rate of oxidation of ingested cystine in the organism of the rabbit. (Box 1)
  - 1931
    - Comparative studies of the metabolism of the amino acids: IV. Phenylalanine and tyrosine. (Box 1)
    - Cystinuria and tuberculosis. (Box 1)
    - Glycogen formation in the white rat after oral administration of xylose. (Box 1)
  - 1932
    - Comparative studies of the metabolism of the amino acids: V. The oxidation of phenylalanine and phenylpyruvic acid in the organism of the rabbit. (Box 1)
    - The chemistry and metabolism of the compounds of sulfur. (Box 1)
    - Cystinuria: a review of some recent investigations. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: XVIII. The distribution of urinary sulfur in the rabbit after the administration of monobromobenzene. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: XIX. The distribution of urinary sulfur in the dog after the oral administration of monobromobenzene as influenced by the character of the dietary protein and by the feeding of l-cystine and dl-methionine. (Box 1)
    - The occurrence of cystinuria in healthy young men and women. (Box 1)
    - Pentose metabolism: I. The rate of absorption of d-xylose and the formation of glycogen in the organism of the white rat after oral administration of d-xylose. II. The pentose content of the tissues of the white rat after the oral administration of d-xylose. (Box 1)
    - The role of amino acids in the animal organism. (Box 1)
    - The tyrosine content of cocoons of various species. (Box 1)
  - 1933
    - The chemistry and metabolism of the compounds of sulfur. (Box 1)
    - Glycogen formation after oral administration of mannitol to white rats. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: XX. The rate of absorption of dl-methionine from the gastrointestinal tract of the white rat. (Box 1)
    - Pentose metabolism: III. The rate of absorption of l-rhamnose and the formation of glycogen in the organism of the white rat after oral administration of l-rhamnose. (Box 1)
    - Studies in the synthesis of hippuric acid in the animal organism: VIII. Hydrazine intoxication and hippuric acid synthesis in the rabbit. (Box 1)
    - Studies in the synthesis of hippuric acid in the animal organism: IX. A comparative study of the rate of synthesis and excretion of hippuric and phenaceturic acids by the rabbit. (Box 1)
  - 1934
    - Comparative studies of the metabolism of amino acids: VI. The rate of absorption of leucine, valine, and their isomers from the gastrointestinal tract of the white rat. (Box 1)
    - The effect of fasting, refeeding, and of variations in the cystine content of the diet on the composition of the tissue proteins of the white rat. (Box 1)
  - 1935
    - The chemistry and metabolism of the compounds of sulfur. (Box 1)
    - Editorial review: the chief sulfur compounds in nutrition. (Box 1)
    - Some products of partial hydrolysis of silk fibroin. (Box 1)
    - Specific rotation of cystine excreted in cystinuria. (Box 1)
    - The utilization of inulin for growth by the young white rat. (Box 1)
  - 1936
    - The metabolism of sulfur: XXIII. The influence of the ingestion of cystine, cysteine, and methionine on the excretion of cystine in cystinuria.1937 (Box 1)
    - Cystine in Normal and cystinuric human blood. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: XXIV. The metabolism of taurine, cysteic acid, cystine, and of some peptides containing these amino acids. (Box 1)
  - 1938
    - The amino acid content of cow and chimpanzee hair. (Box 1)
    - Availability of dibenzoylcystine for growth of the young white rat. (Box 1)
    - Comparative studies of the metabolism of the amino acids: VII. Experimental alcaptonuria in the white rat. (Box 1)
    - The enzymatic digestion of wool. (Box 1)
    - Excretion of homogentisic acid after oral administration of phenylalanine to alcaptonuric subjects. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: XXV. Dietary methionine as a factor related to the growth and composition of the hair of the young white rat. (Box 1)
  - 1939
    - Comparative studies of the metabolism of the amino acids: VIII. Glycine precursors. Availability of n-methylglycine, n,n-dimethylglycine, and betaine for the synthesis of hippuric acid by the rabbit. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: XXVI. The metabolism of the betaine of cystine. (Box 1)
    - Quantitative determination of selenium in tissues and feces. (Box 1)
    - The retention and excretion of selenium after the administration of sodium selenite to white rats. (Box 1)
    - The synthesis of dicholylcystine and cholylcysteic acid. (Box 1)
  - 1940
    - Dietary protein and the toxicity of sodium selenite in the white rat. (Box 1)
    - The excretion of volatile selenium compounds after the administration of sodium selenite to white rats. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of proteins and amino acids. (Box 1)
    - Charles Wallis Edmunds. (Box 1)
    - End products of nitrogen metabolism in animals.1941 (Box 1)
    - Comparative studies of the metabolism of the amino acids: IX. Glycine precursors. Availability of n-ethylglycine and glycolic acid for the synthesis of hippuric acid by the rabbit. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: XXVII. The distribution of sulfur in the ultrafiltrates of blood plasma. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: XXIX. S-carboxymethylcysteine. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: XXX. Thiourea. (Box 1)
    - The significance of the sulfur-containing amino acids in metabolism. (Box 1)
  - 1942
    - Handbook of nutrition: II. Proteins in nutrition. (Box 1)
    - The preparation of 4(5)-hydroxymethylimidazole. (Box 1)
    - Urocanic acid and the intermediary metabolism of histidine in the rabbit. (Box 1)
  - 1943
    - Experimental lathyrism in the white rat. (Box 1)
    - The utilization of d-glucono--lactone by the organism of the young white rat. (Box 1)
    - Trends in vitamin research. (Box 1)
  - 1944
    - The composition of the tissue proteins of the rabbit as influenced by inanition and the hepatotoxic agents, hydrazine and phosphorus. (Box 1)
    - Glucuronic acid synthesis and the glycogen content of the liver of the rat. (Box 1)
    - The partition of urinary nitrogen after the oral administration of glutamic acid, pyrrolidonecarboxylic acid, proline, and hydroxyproline to rabbits. (Box 1)
    - Russell Henry Chittenden, 1856-1943 (Box 1)
  - 1945
    - The metabolism of trimethylacetic (pivalic) and tertiary butylacetic acid. New examples of conjugation with glucuronic acid. (Box 1)
  - 1946
    - The metabolism of sulfur: XXXI. The distribution of urinary sulfur and the excretion of keto acids after the oral administration of some derivatives of cystine and methionine to the rabbit. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of sulfur: XXXII. Isocysteine. (Box 1)
    - O Metabolismo Intermediario e o Papel Nutritivo dos Acidos Aminados Aromaticos e Sulfurados da Molecula Proteica. (Box 1)
  - 1947
    - A comparative study of the metabolism of-alanine,-alanine, serine, and isoserine: I. Absorption from the gastrointestinal tract. (Box 1)
    - A comparative study of the metabolism of-alanine,-alanine, serine, and isoserine: II. Glycogen content of the liver after oral administration of the amino acids. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of phenoxyacetic acid, its homologues, and some monochlorophenoxyacetic acids. New examples of oxidation. (Box 1)
    - Nutrition. (Box 1)
  - 1948
    - Alkaline phosphatase of the serum in experimental lathyrism of the white rat. (Box 1)
    - The nutritive value of some legumes. Lathyrism in the rat. The sweet pea (lathyrus odoratus), lathyrus sativus, lathyrus cicera and some other species of lathyrus. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of p-aminosalicylic acid in the organism of the rabbit. (Box 1)
  - 1949
    - Experimental lathyrism in the white rat and mouse. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of some branched chain aliphatic acids. (Box 1)
    - The nitrogenous metabolism of the earthworm (lumbricus terrestris). (Box 1)
    - Protein metabolism in disease. (Box 1)
  - 1950
    - Amino acids of Bence-Jones protein. (Box 1)
    - Biochemical studies on urokon (sodium 2, 4, 6-triiodo-3-acetylaminobenzoate), a new pyelographic medium. (Box 1)
    - The metabolism of p-aminobenzoic acid in the rabbit. (Box 1)
    - Niacin and the ability of cystine to augment deposition of liver fat. (Box 1)
    - The nitrogenous metabolism of the earthworm (lumbricus terrestris): II. Arginase and urea synthesis.1951 (Box 1)
    - The histidine content of the urine in pregnancy. (Box 1)
    - The supplemental value of cystine and methionine for low protein (casein) diets fed the young white rat. (Box 1)
  - 1952
    - Experimental lathyrism. (19785) (Box 1)
    - Fifty years of study of the role of protein in nutrition. (Box 1)
    - Protein. (Box 1)
  - 1953
    - Diet and the ergothioneine content of blood. (Box 1)
    - Synthesis of hippuric acid and benzoyl glucuronide by the rabbit. (Box 1)
  - Undated
    - Biochemistry in the pharmacy curriculum--optional or required subject. (Box 1)
    - Proteins in nutrition. Lewis, Howard Bishop, 1887-1954, Pamphlets and Reprints. (Box 1)
Related Material
Bentley Library's also has personal manuscript collection of professor Lewis. See: Howard B. Lewis papers, 1922-1954. His work as dean of the College of Pharmacy is also a record group. See: College of Pharmacy (University of Michigan) records, 1868-1994